I
they said
welcome everybody welcome to BSD v. GPL
personaly i'd like to thank the organizers
and the volunteers for making the New York City BSDCon
possible
and my employer OmniTI
for sponsoring my talk
I had to get that in
a couple years ago I was invited to give a talk here
that was quite quite a lot of fun to give and seemed
be well received
fortunately they were fool hardy enough to invite me
back again
but as we know sequels really measure up so
the official title of this is
not the sequel to "BSD is Dying"
but don't worry it's just as short as the first one
BSD v. GSL the great debate
the ongoing conflict between users of the BSD
and GPL licenses
well what is the debate
do you mean like
gosh Jason
I didn't know there was a debate between
the BSD and GPL licenses
or like duh Jason
everyone knows that
BSD has already won
well for the sake of argument
let's assume that we're talking about the former
so back to the debate
which license is more free
it depends a lot on how you define freedom
is it a tool used to guarantee the freedom of the code
for everyone
or is it a mechanism
providing select freedoms
to a select group of users
I'll let you make that judgment for yourselfs
but first let's step back in time a moment
look at the origins of the BSD
and GPL licenses
which should help us better understand their
goals and philosophies
I know boo
even though work on the ancestors of UNIX
dates back to nineteen seventy four
it took roughly fifteen years to get to
a point where these licenses became a necessity
back in nineteen eighty five
Richard Stallman
a member of the staff at MIT
had a dispute
with the company named UniPress
another developer named James Gosling
developed the first version of Emacs written in C
after Stallman had incorporated parts Goslings Emacs
into Gnu Emacs
Gosling sold the rights to UniPress
UniPress theatened Stallman
against further redistribution of the Gosling bits
so he rewote the effected portions
and released a new version under a copyleft license
call Emacs General Public License
the June nineteen eighty eight issue
of the GNU bulletion
first mentioned that GNU general public
license
but even his earlest announcement foreshadowed
an underlying theme that forms the great debate
switching gears
switching gears we find ourselves
in the summer of 1989
soaking up the summer rays in the computer
lab
of CSRG of Cal Berkeley
the Berkeley Software Distribution
already had thousands of copies distributed to
users
because the releases included the source code
AT&T Unix
as well as Berkeley's improvements
users were required to purchase
an AT&T source license
demand had built up
for a version of BSD Unix
that didn't require an AT&T source license
so BSD developers were able to put together a
release
free of AT&T code
that included the BSD originated TCP/IP networking
stack and it's supported utilities
this version was officially known as Networking Release 1
or NET/1
and was released under a liberal license
were the user could redistribute the code
modified or unmodified
source or binary form
with no accounting of roylaties to Berkeley
even with these liberal terms
hundreds of organizations step forward to paid
the one thousand dollar fee
for copies of the official NET/1 media
by 1991 the free software community had
considerable momentum
with the success of the GNU
compiler collection of userland tools
berkeley's own networking release 2
GPLv2 and the LGPL
and the linux kernel
a fledgling knockoff of MINIX
created by a student
at the University of Helsinki
come 1992 the BSD community
was buckling up for a wild right
Unix Systems Laboratories
a subsidiary of AT&T
filed suit against BSDI
claiming that their derivative of Berkeley's NET/2
infringed on the official the AT&T copyrights
by 1994
the lawsuit was settled
largely in favor of BSDI and Cal Berkeley
but the impact of BSD adoption was
substantial
hello
new users gravitated to the Linux and
GNU alternative in droves
resulting in increased acceptance
of Stallman's GPL license and new manifesto
with a little bit of history under our belt
we can begin to take a deeper look at the
goals of each license
and the means it uses
and I means it uses to reach those ends
certainly these two licenses share
some common goals
they're both OSI approved licenses
suitable
for a variety of software projects
both licenses require attribution to remain intact
typically in the form of a copyright notice
within the license
every developer reserves the right to point
a completed works and take credit for their
efforts
admittedly some may choose not too
we don't have any MySQL developers in here do we
both licenses
but licenses convey freedoms to the user
to use the code as he or she sees fit
to read and learn from the code
use the resulting binaries
to develop your own applications
and stick it to your favorite three letter agencies
both licenses allow users
to redistribute
source code in binary forms
provided certain conditions are met
we'll come back to this in a few moments
both licenses provide some basic disclaimers
as a layer of protection for the developer
against claims of liability
for any direct
indirect
incidental
exemplary
thats a really hard one to get a picture of
or consequential damages
including but not limited to
procurement of substitute goods and services
loss of use,
loss of data,
lost profits,
or business interuption
I'd like to say that I did this slide before this
week
anyone who knows me knows that's not true
as we've seen both BSD and GPL licences share
some common freedoms
but as we know the devil's in the details
I'd actually like to ask for audience participation
in the following slides
this is my own experiment
to help gadge the communities familiarity with
the licenses
I'm going to read off a phrase
and I'd like you all to tell me which license
it is applicable too
k lets begin
freedom for everyone
even businesses
BSD
anti-capitalist socialism
GPL
thank you
that's correct
easy compliance
force code
to remain open
GDL
world domination
BSD
perhaps FreeBSD
I'll give you half credit
shut up and hack
brief and simple
BSD
complex and obtuse
this is not the ASB graph this is
something someone pointed to online
it represents the word count in each
version of the BSD and GPL licenses
yes and I think that that's true
the the for and third up losses
it was over the issue it before
take that as you will
and I mentioned previously that both include
some conditions regarding distribution
this in particular is where you see a real diversion
philosophies
the GPL license includes a number of
terms and conditions
intent on restricting the sale, use
and redistribution of the effect it works
let's look at the examples
first
your aloowed to copy and distribute the program source code
so long as you include
the copyright notice
the disclaimer of warrenty
and any notices that refer to the license
I wasn't sure that anybody would get this
you may also charge a fee for packaging or
transferal of the work
or offer warrenty protection for a fee
but you may not sell the software
you can copy or distribute any derivative works
providing you meet the following conditions
any modified files most prominently displayed
notice that the files were changed
it must be a license as a whole and no charge
to any thrid parties
and if the program reads commands interactivly when run
it must display an announcement
including a copyright notice and disclaimer
of warrenty
you may copy or distribute the code in binary form
provided you meet these conditions
you include the corresponding source code
a written offer
valid for at least three years
to provide any third party with a copy of the
source code
for a fee not to exceed the cost of distributing the source code
there are other restrictions as well we have covered
the most intrusive ones
the other is a mass of while the religious
right
to be fair the FCC licenses and without its
own restrictions
most of the issue mainstream the is the distributions
such as previously majesty
and ratified is the up for further to cosby
is the lessons for nafta
the only issue brought it goes one step further
using the issue like a modified highest the
license with no extra cost
but again even these have a number of his
first reactions use our freedoms
here's an exhaustive lives
of these restrictions
activists loyal there
no more free license is the easier it is to
comply
conversely the more complex a license becomes
the more likely it is that violations her
the saw for freedom law center
offers legal representation
the free and open source offer projects
the web site lead you to believe that they
defend the rights of all streets are process
but would review the press releases
shows that every single case it's a has been
released
in fact many of you may remember last year
when will it makes their story developers
realizing straight floaters
obviously if they're struggling the jeep you
know
what you saw
what they also removed rates copyright points
that the case
the software freedom also stepped in
in convince limits developers to correct the
rich states
but not until a storm of controversy was unleashed
causing hardship among the lyrics and the
it's the communities
the press releases carefully worded
to make it safe
to make it sound like they were betting
you can be as the license for compatibility
rather than explaining how the limits developers
infringed on race right
does anyone else in also
because copyright a softer also complex
the number of missus claus up we're going
to be as easy going as this is
i'd like to conclude my top
but they're not few days
this is number one
did you get a license is more free
although places restrictions on users
the integrity of freedom
possibly forcing uses to publish their changes
results in a greater level of freedom
the restrictions always means less free
what did the original developer
born in danger
did you kill always places additional restrictions
on the economy
modification
redistribution effect it works
that number two
the issue through to be still
he also claim that because the company can
take care
make the changes proprietary
that somehow lessons
the freemen's of the original up
this is completed on a ship
the result was always this tree is a ritual
developers she said
no evil corporation to subvert the rights
of other users to the the issue is
number three
so Richard Stallman is a socialist
intent on destroying commercial software companies
yes
I
Richard Stallman actually congress
intent on destroying commercial software companies
socialism actually from a state ownership
it means of production
rather
Stallman believes in the class of state fourteen
days of all the rules